Arthur E. Goldschmidt papers, 1913-2001 (bulk 1960-2001) 00399
Eberly Family Special Collections Library
Arthur E. Goldschmidt papers
1913-2001
1960-2001
Eberly Family Special Collections Library
00399
10 Cubic feet
Arthur E, Goldschmidt was appointed an assistant professor of history at The Pennsylvania State University in 1965, specializing in the history of modern Egypt. He became an associate professor in 1973 and visiting associate professor of Middle East history at the University of Haifa from 1973 to 1974. He was appointed a full professor of history in 1989. He retired in 2000 with emeritus status.
This collection of the papers of history professor Arthur E. Goldschmidt documents his research and teaching. Materials include correspondence, newspaper clippings, articles, programs, reports, speeches, publications, five audio recordings of Goldschmidt, and class materials.
Biographical or Historical Note
Dr. Arthur E. Goldschmidt, Jr. was born in Washington, DC in 1938. He received his A.B. at Colby College in 1959, his A.M. at Harvard University in 1961 and his Ph.D. in 1968. He was appointed an assistant professor of history at The Pennsylvania State University in 1965 and became an associate professor in 1973 and visiting associate professor of Middle East history at the University of Haifa from 1973 to 1974. He was appointed a full professor of history in 1989. He retired in 2000 with emeritus status.A specialist on modern Egypt, he published articles and book reviews in professional journals and was awarded research fellowships by the Social Science Research Council and the American Research Center in Egypt. He was a member of the Committee on Biographical Projects of the Middle East Studies Association and served as a consultant to a project to computerize the political and diplomatic history of the Arab world between 1900 and 1967. In 1981, he was awarded a citation in the first national Professor of the Year competition sponsored by the Council for Advancement and Support of Education (CASE).
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Audio
- Encart Encyclopedia - Egypt: Government and History, 1998-2005 (Box 11)
- Correspondence with Lynne Rienner - Biographical Dictionary, 1995-2010 (Box 11)
- History in Dispute - David Lesch, 2003 (Box 11)
- Encyclopedia of Middle East and North Africa, 2nd ed., 2003 (Box 11)
- Literature of Travel and Exploration - Wilfred S. Blunt entry, 1999 (Box 11)
- Entries for Oxford Encyclopedia of the Modern World, 2005 (Box 11)
- Goldschmidt, Arthur Jr. - Research and Writing: Projects and Papers, Undated (Box 7)
- Goldschmidt, Arthur Jr. - Research and Writing: Projects and Papers, Undated (Box 8)
- Goldschmidt, Arthur Jr. - Research and Writing: Projects and Papers, Undated (Box 9)
- Goldschmidt, Arthur Jr. - Research and Writing: Projects and Papers, Undated (Box 10)
- Liberal Arts Council of Senators, 1984-1985 (Box 2)
- Correspondence, 1990 (Box 2)
- Middle East is Governments and Politics book, Undated (Box 2)
- General Egyptian Book Organization, 1983 (Box 2)
- National Defense Foreign Language Fellowship correspondence, 1960-1965 (Box 2)
- Biographical Dictionary of Modern Egypt correspondence, 1969-1971 (Box 2)
- Egyptian Biographical Dictionary Lists, Undated (Box 2)
- Historical Dictionary of Egypt, 1994 (Box 2)
- Encyclopedia of Modern Middle East Correspondence and Research Notes for Entries, Undated (Box 2)
- Alternative Employment correspondence, 1964-1969 (Box 2)
- Concise History of Middle East (Maps for Editions 1-5), Undated (Box 2)
- Harvard and Grade Reports, Undated (Box 2)
- Pennsylvania Arabs, 1966-1968 (Box 2)
- Published Book Reviews, 1969 (Box 2)
- Correspondence with Libraries and Archives, 1963-1983 (Box 2)
- Social Sciences 127 Term Papers, 1959-1960 (Box 2)
- History 187 Essay, 1961/03/31 (Box 2)
- Government 296, 1961/05/18 (Box 2)
- History 232B, 1962/01/22 (Box 2)
- Government 120, 1961/01/20 (Box 2)
- Farid Diaries Memoirs English Translation, 1913 (Box 2)
- Farid Memoirs Translation Mellen Press, 1991 (Box 2)
- Leave of Absence, 1969 (Box 2)
- Report to Newsletter of American Research Center in Egypt, 1969 (Box 2)
- Haifa University Sabbatical Leave, 1973-1974 (Box 2)
- Cairo University Fulbright Program - Sabbatical Leave, 1981-1982 (Box 2)
- Research and Travel to England, 1989 (Box 2)
- Durham University Sabbatical Leave, 1990-1991 (Box 2)
- Arabian Peninsula proposed trips, 1995-1997 (Box 2)
- American Research Center in Egypt Sabbatical Leave, 1997-1998 (Box 2)
- English - Original Version of Arabic article, Undated (Box 2)
- Almussarrar Newsletter, 1969/11/14 (Box 2)
- Baker, Paul Show on WHP, 1991/08/16; Audio Cassette Standard (Box 2)
- Radio Interview, 1991/01/31; Audio Cassette Standard (Box 2)
- Speaking on Middle East at Quadrange Retirement Community, 1991/05/16; Audio Cassette Standard (Box 2)
- Interview on Penn State Radio, 1994; Audio Cassette Standard (Box 2)
- Penn State Schuylkill Campus Talk, 1991/02/05; Audio Cassette Standard (Box 2)
- Goldschmidt, Arthur Jr. - Materials Pertaining to History 10 (Non-Western Civilization), 1981-1999 (Box 4)
- Goldschmidt, Arthur Jr. - Committee Service New Jersey Scholars, 1985 (Box 4)
- Goldschmidt, Arthur Jr. - Course Handouts, Lectures, Discussion Outlines (400-UP), Undated (Box 5)
- Goldschmidt, Arthur Jr. - Elderhostel Courses, Undated (Box 5)
- Goldschmidt, Arthur Jr. - Course Handouts, Lectures, Discussion Outlines (History 11, 19, 181, 191), Undated (Box 6)
- Correspondence, 1992-1995 (Box 1)
- Published Writings, offprints, 1982-1993 (Box 1)
- Sabbatical Leave, 1981-1982 (Box 1)
- PHD Candidates (work with), 1968-1993 (Box 1)
- Harvard College Commencement, 1968 (Box 1)
- Satanic Verses, Controversy, Undated (Box 1)
- Semester at Sea, 1987 (Box 1)
- Semester at Sea, 1983-1997 (Box 1)
- Undergraduate Middle East Conferences, 1987-1989 (Box 1)
- Research Grants, 1986-1998 (Box 1)
- Speeches, 1982-2000 (Box 1)
- Gulf War - Speeches and Newspaper Articles, 1991 (Box 1)
- Pennsylvania Humanities Council Speaking Stint, 1989 (Box 3)
- Modern Egypt draft chapters, 1986 (Box 3)
- Draft materials for History 10 reader (Box 3)
- Duquesne History Forum, 1983 (Box 3)
- International Military Encyclopedia, 1982-1987 (Box 3)
- UPCLOSE, 1980-1984 (Box 3)
- Articles on "Arab League" and "Middle East History" for Funk and Wagnall's Encyclopedia, 1980 (Box 3)
- Concise History of Middle East - students' notes for 1983 revision (Box 3)
- AMOCO and CASE teaching awards, 1981 (Box 3)
- Concise History of Middle East - 1978 version - Glenn Perry comments (Box 3)
- Middle East Studies Association - Research and Training (RATS), 1975-1979 (Box 3)
- Perspective on the 1980's Task Force: "Students and Society", circa 1980-1989 (Box 3)
- Griswold-Perry Project (Box 3)
- Islamic Teaching Materials Project, 1973-1975 (Box 3)
- Secretarial work for the College of the Liberal Arts, 1978-1979 (Box 3)
- Academic Advising Award and subsequent committee work, 1976 (Box 3)
- Middle East History proposed syllabus for University of Pennsylvania, 1975-1977 (Box 3)
- Borthwick, Bruce politics text critique, 1974-1982 (Box 3)
- Agriculture speaking engagements and clippings, 1980 (Box 3)
- Agriculture speaking engagements and clippings, 1974-1979 (Box 3)
- Agriculture speaking engagements and clippings, 1974-1979 (Box 3)
- Program review: East Asian Studies, 1975 (Box 3)
- Class of 1933 Humanities Award 1972 and subsequent committee work 1973-1975, 1972-1975 (Box 3)
- Heravi - Middle East dictionary, 1969 (Box 3)
- Correspondence and Newspaper Clippings, 1981-2000 (Box 1)
- Middle East Encyclopedia Sources, 2005-2006 (Box 11)
- Contemporary Middle East:: Westview Reader, 2005 (Box 11)
- The Egyptian Nationalist Party - revised dissertation - not published (Box 11)
- The Egyptian Nationalist Party - revised dissertation - not published (Box 11)
- The Egyptian Nationalist Party - revised dissertation - not published (Box 11)
- The Egyptian Nationalist Party - original version of PhD dissertation, 1965 (Box 11)
- The Egyptian Nationalist Party - original version of PhD dissertation, 1965 (Box 11)
- The Egyptian Nationalist Party - original version of PhD dissertation, 1965 (Box 11)
- Concise History of the Middle East - 2nd ed. - typescript manuscript, 1982 (Box 11)
- Concise History of the Middle East - 2nd ed. - typescript manuscript, 1982 (Box 11)
- Concise History of the Middle East - 2nd ed. - typescript manuscript, 1982 (Box 11)
- Concise History of the Middle East - 2nd ed. - typescript manuscript, 1982 (Box 11)
- Concise History of the Middle East - 2nd ed. - typescript manuscript, 1982 (Box 11)
- Historical Dictionary of Egypt (rev. ed.) - typed manuscript, 1994 (Box 1)
- Historical Dictionary of Egypt (rev. ed.) - typed manuscript, 1994 (Box 1)
- Historical Dictionary of Egypt (rev. ed.) - typed manuscript, 1994 (Box 1)
- Historical Dictionary of Egypt (rev. ed.) - typed manuscript, 1994 (Box 1)
- Re-Envisioning Egypt, 2003-2005 (Box 11)
- Encylopedia of African History - articles, 1999 (Box 11)
- Berkshire Women's History Conference, 1978 (Box 11)
- Encylopedia Britannica - Egypt, 2007 (Box 11)
- Encylopedia Britannica - Egypt article revision, 2000 (Box 11)
- Concise History of the Middle East - 8th ed. - correspondence with Lawrence Davidson, 2004-2005 (Box 11)
- Concise History of the Middle East - 8th ed. - proofs for photographs, 2004-2005 (Box 11)
- Concise History of the Middle East - 8th ed. - publisher correspondence, 2004-2005 (Box 11)
- Concise History of the Middle East - 8th ed. - revisions, 2004-2005 (Box 11)
- Concise History of the Middle East - 7th ed., 1997-2001 (Box 11)
- Understanding the Contemporary Middle East - 2nd ed., 2004 (Box 11)